Hey guys, Shandra said welcome back to
the channel. So today we will start with
retry and we have already covered rate
limiter in part one, bulkhead in part
two, time limiter we are not going to
cover we will cover it when we will do
reactive programming. So let's start
without wasting any time and uh before I
start I just want to say that that retry
if we not properly implemented it has
more disadvantage than advantage. We
will get to know why. So in distributed
system call to downstream service might
fail because of transient issues.
Transient issues means that short
temporary issue like network issue,
timeout etc. and retry of same request
after a short delay can get succeed.
Okay. So one question might comes to you
that hey
still why we should do retry?
Why can't user or client can invoke our
API again? So let's say that this is our
client.
This is our component order and we have
an API
and we are invoking another API of let's
say product component
and
there is some transient issue while
invoking it. So what we are saying is so
transient issues if we retry it it can
get succeed. So we can do a retry for
this invocation. So the question is that
hey shange why we need to retry why
can't client again invoke the API so
that automatically it will invoke the
product API again why we have to retry
ourself. So see the answer is for each
call lot of heavy processing is done and
it's not free of cost
memory time resources etc. So everything
like it's there is some cost incurred.
So say you have invoke client at first
invoke an API 90% of the API
implementation is completed task is
completed only 10% is left and then it
invoke this product API and the
transient issue happen let's say uh
network timeout happen so is it a good
idea to dispose of this 90% of the task
which is done no right we if we can just
simply retry this and if it gets
succeeded then only 10% task have to be
done otherwise if we ask client to retry
again our API hit again our API again we
will do the same 90% task again so
redundant of the work is there duplicacy
of the work is there and it will
increase our cost and it's not free of
cost to be honest right
so with above understanding we know know
that retry is important right I think I
hope this point will tell you that why
retry is important because we don't want
to do the same 90% task again okay and
I'm just saying this is just one client
if there are 100 clients for this API
and they are all invoking and there are
thousands of calls so you are saying
that you are doing lot of wasting your
uh capacity on just duplicate task which
you have already completed.
So we know that retry is important but
the now question is when to retry, how
to retry. Very very important question.
When to retry? First of all is do not
retry on permanent failures. Permanent
failures is like no matter how many
times you will retry, it will always
fail like 4xx errors. So 4xx errors
generally are in the category of
validation error.
Validation error. Validation error means
the input request input request which
client has passed has is not correct
until unless client will not change the
input
validation error will not remove. So if
you retry with the same request
previously again you will see a
validation error. So generally these are
known as permanent failure. 4xx
do not retry if operation is
nonidopatent.
What doesopetent means? So idopotent see
make sure that if request is retried
multiple times duplicate processing will
not happen. So say you have a service A
which invokes the create API of service
B. Okay. So it has invoked it and while
service B write it into its DB but it
takes certain time okay and here it say
that timeout happen and timeout happens.
So for service A the request has been
timeout but service B internally
inserted the row into the DB.
Now since this is a timeout and user has
retried so this is a retrieded again.
Now here service B insert the row again
ID2 earlier it was already inserted ID 1
now it is ID2 so here this is not my
intention my intention was not to create
a duplicate row for the same request
okay so we can say that this this API
the API of the service B this create API
is not idopent
okay so that's why we say that do not
retry if operation is nonidopent
Otherwise you will end up in creating
duplicate resources.
So if you don't know how to design
idotent APIs I have already covered it
into the highle design playlist uh in
depth like what are the challenges how
we can come up with the adoptent API
design. So have a look uh in case you
have a doubt. Okay. So but here
one thing is we don't have to retry if
operation is nonopertent.
The third is that rule of thumb says
that retry only on 5xx error. What 5xx
error says that it is system error. Your
input request input request is good.
Okay. All validation passed but there is
some limitation in system or some issue
happen in the system because of that
error has happened. So generally these
are considered as retriable error. Okay.
So it is safe to retry on this because
this is first of all system error and
also it says that it request is not
successful means the previous request 5s
means request is not successful.
Okay. So that is also one give us a you
can say that u relief that yeah previous
request is not successful and we can
retry as many times. So there is no
harm. Okay.
And 5xs already know that input request
is correct. No validation errors but
there is some issue with the system. So
with retry it is possible that it might
get resolved.
So that is one and another thing is
retry network uh network error and
timeout error we have to retry but only
make sure that whatever the API it
should support adoptency.
So this is a retry decision table like
based on HTTP code you can decide
whether you have to retry or not. So
these are not complete list just an idea
let's say 200
request is already success you don't
have to retry like 400 bad request
unauthorized forbidden 404 not found so
these are you can say that validation
error no matter how many times you will
retry you will always get retribal
failure uh failure itself right so you
don't have to retry on this so 4 to9 you
can say that one of the exception like 4
to9 9 means too many requests. So it
generally happen when the rate limiting.
So for that we can do retry with some
delay. Then we have 500 internal server
error. 502 bad gateway 503 service
unavailable. These are like uh you can
say that retryable issue like service
unavailable. Maybe it was down and if
you retry it might be up and it request
can get succeeded. So for all this we
can do retry and if there is a network
error timeouts you can always retry yes
but make sure that it should be idopent.
Okay so this is just a quick glance that
based on http status code you decide
whether the retry can be done or not.
Now how to retry? So see this is very
important part. So let's see first types
of retry and when and then we will see
how to implement it also. So first is
fixed interval retry.
So what does fixed interval retry says
that retry after a constant delay. So
within each retry the delay is constant.
So say that the attempt total attempt is
four.
So when we say total attempt means
original one call plus three retries. So
total four. Okay. So after original call
there has to be a fixed delay like let's
say my fixed delay is 2 second. So it
would be like after 2 seconds first
retry will happen. Then it will wait for
2 second then second retry will happen.
Then it will wait for 2 seconds then
third retry will happen. So there is a
fixed interval of delay within the
retries. So let's say this is the
original call which happened at two. So
first uh retry happen at four. Then
second retrive will six. Third retrive
at eight. So each one has two two
seconds gap say.
So advantage of this is it is very very
simple easy to configure and debug also.
But this is main this disadvantage is
that higher chance of retry storm
which is also known as thundering her
problem. Thundering her problem mean
many clients retry at the same time
causing a surge of retry traffic and
system spend resources on retries
instead of handling new request. So
understand with this is that say that
you have a load balancer
and you have let's say component service
A
service A multiple instances
instance one instance two instance three
and load balancer distribute the traffic
between the instances of service A there
are so many clients client one client N
and the traffic is also huge now let's
say that a buggy code has been
introduced into the service A and it
start throwing some exception and if
client start doing retry also is already
it's a heavy traffic and for that they
are all started doing retry at a fixed
delay so all are retrying so original
request let's say there are thousand
request original now after 2C delay
Okay,
retry one will happen. Okay. So everyone
will do retry 1 th00and requests again
after 2 second delay retry two they
again do a retry.
Okay. So these are just retry traffic.
Whatever the normal traffic new request
is coming that is different. So means
your system is now get bombarded with
the retry traffic. And it is possible
that while you are only servicing retry
traffic, you somehow declined the new
request which is coming. That is also
possible.
Okay. So I if you remember like in the
HLD playlist I have already covered
thundering her problem like it is one of
the frequently asked interview question.
So if you want to know more about
thundering earth problem you can check
it out. But yeah this is one of the
disadvantage is that if all the clients
retry at the same interval it is
possible that the retry traffic become
huge and it can cause thundering her
problem.
So fixed interval is clear then we have
exponential back off. So what does
exponential back off says that delay
increases exponentially.
So currently earlier you are delaying at
this time then this time then this time
not at fixed rate not after 2 seconds
this is 2 second not at fixed so it
increase with the time and this is the
formula for it. So the formula says that
you pick some base delay that yeah
minimum base delay is my 100 millisecond
into two raised to power this is a
factor you can say that this is also
configurable factor raised to power
number of failed retry attempt. Okay so
consider that total attempt is four
means one original call and three
retries and my base is 100. So the
formula says that the first retry will
so let's say original call happen at uh
0 0 millcond say so first retry will
happen at 100 which is our base delay
into and the factor which I have given
is let's say this factor I have given is
two for now 2 raised to power previous
number of failed retry attempt currently
this is the first retry itself so zero
no retry attempt has failed. So
currently it is zero. So this is first
retry happen at so original call happen
at 0 millisecond. First retry will
happen at 100 millisecond. Second retry
will happen at 100 base into whatever
the factor you have told. Let's say I
have told two raised to power number of
failed retry attempt. So till now only
one retry attemp failed. So it's one. So
retry will happen at 200 millisecond.
Third retry will happen at 100 into 2 to
power number of failed retry time two
till now two retry has been done. So 2^
400 millisecond. So now here is if you
see the delay time is exponentially
increases 100 200 400 next you will see
800 like this.
So advantage is that it reduce the load
on downstream service during outage.
Let's say that this service become
this service become down.
If we increase the delay, they also get
some breathing time to recover it.
Unnecessary. If you put the load of the
retry also plus the original request
also the it might take some more time to
recover for the component
and it also helps to avoid thundering
her problem to some extent. Right? Since
they are not returning at a constant
time it delays. So thundering her heart
problem you can say that uh to some
extent it reduces.
But does it reduce fully? No. There is
still risk of thundering her because see
this is the formula. What if your base
is my base all the client select the
same base and same factor then they will
retry at the same time itself. So there
is because there is no randomness right.
So there is a still a chance of
thundering her problem
and also if outage period is short user
might wait some longer time. So let's
say that
this shortage is resolved at 500
millisecond. After 500 millcond this
outage was resolved but after 400
millisecond the delay was 800 only after
that it will retry. So there is even
though the issue was resolved it still
added some latency right the outage
period is short user might wait longer
than needed. So this is one of the
disadvantage.
So there is one another version of it is
like exponential back off plus jitter.
Jitter means some randomness
similar to exponential backoff but add
jitterness or randomness
to delay
or to you can say that to avoid retry
storms. Now see exponential backoff
already
uh increases the delay time
exponentially right but only thing which
missing is randomness. So this
jitterness
helps to retry uh reduce the retry
storms. So this is its formula.
We have to choose a random number
between random between
0 comma minimum of maximum delay. What
what is the maximum delay
we can have? Let's say no exponential
back off. So it's not like let's say you
have for example I'm just saying you
have 100 retry so it's not like it
continuously increases the time and all
no there should always be limit right
after a limit this is the maximum wait
time let's say uh 5 second this is the
maximum delay time more than that you
can't go increase if you more than
increase if your for with the formula if
it gives you the value of more than 5
second always use 5 seconds so this is
the maximum limit.
So here is the same random you have to
choose a random between 0 comma minimum
of the maximum delay or this is our
exponential backoff formula.
Okay. So now we have bring some
randomness.
So again random between
0 comma minimum of maximum delay which
we can wait comma your exponential
backoff
formula one.
So between these it now pick some delay
value and now since this is random you
can say that uh it spread the retries
over time reduce peak load and
thundering her issue is pro happening of
this issue become very less because of
this randomness.
The disadvantage is it's not easy to
debug and it's little complex.
And the last type of retry is custom
interval like you define your own retry
logic. Hey, I want retry to be like 1 1
2 3 5 like this. Okay. So first retry
should wait for 1 sec 1 millisecond then
another 1 millisecond then 2 millcond
then 3 millcond then five then 8 like
this. So you can define your own custom
logic how you want to do a retry that is
also possible. So we have full control
and flexibility but disadvantage is you
have to maintain you have to maintain
it. So you have to write the logic you
have to maintain it. The framework will
not help you in this. We will see that.
So first let's see the implementation of
fixed interval. How you can do that?
This is same controller. This is faint
client interface. controller is invoking
the order service invoke product API.
This service it is invoking.
Now here if you see I have put at the
rate retry com uh annotation on top of
this method. One thing remember is
always use retry on a top of method the
logic which you want to retry. So I only
want to retry this my downstream call.
Let's say if you have some lot of
business logic here everything will get
retry. If you have a DB call that will
also get retry. So please double check
double verify where you are putting this
retry. What all logic are there inside
that method because that will get
executed.
Okay. So I have used at the rate retry
annotation. Give it a name fallback
method. like after all the retry got
failed ultimately this fallback method
will get invoked.
Okay.
Now in the application.properties
here if you see I have defined the
configuration resilience 4j retry
instances product service. This is the
name I have given.
Maximum attempt is three
and resilience 4j retry instances
product service wait duration is 2
seconds.
So now here if you see that I haven't
told which type to use whether it has to
use fixed delay exponential back off or
with jitterness because by default it is
fixed interval by default which
resilience 4j uses retries
fixed interval. Okay and maximum at time
we have defined is three and weight
duration is 2 seconds. So it will wait
2222 seconds.
Now you can you can easily test it. If
you want to test it, you can easily test
it that uh so here in this one I have
just put uh try catch block and in the
catch I have put not able to invoke
product API. So I'm invoking the product
API right? I haven't started it server
itself. I haven't started server. So
definitely it will fail. Not able to
invoke product. So I have just put this
not able to invoke product and let's see
that how many times it will retry it. So
if you see this what is the
configuration we have put three mean one
original call and two retry. So if you
see this first time this is the original
call which happened at 2056
not able to invoke
then it wait for 2 seconds because this
is the delay period we have defined into
this wait duration 2 seconds.
So it happened at 20 5612. So 2 second
delay first retry happened again failed.
After that second retry happened at
25614 again 2C second delay fixed
interval delay not able to invoke and
all the retries finished and then it
says that product service is busy
this is our fallback method
make sense and uh this thing I already
told you that this thing you can have
multiple milliseconds seconds minute you
can even go 500 ms milliseconds
So in that also millisecond also you can
set the values.
Now how internally this might be
working. So see here as we already know
resilience 4j totally relies on AOP and
AOP generates the proxy code right it
generates write the code. So for this
retry what code it might have written.
So see this is the code it EOP might
have written. I am not sure but AOP
because generate the code during runtime
you can't uh debugging is difficult on
that runtime code generation part but
this is the uh framework which retry
uses it so it has multiple parts so
consider as three part first part is
interval function
second is
retry config
third is retry object.
So retry function is the function where
your delay logic resides.
If you open this class ret interval
function, you will see so many
functions. Uh you will see so many
methods. One is off and you have just
wait time. So that is for fixed delay.
Then there is something called
exponential back off.
So that is for exponential backoff uh
retry. So for certain it's already
written. We don't have to have written
this formula by ourself. So inside
interval function class if you go you
will find different methods.
uh one method for exponential back off,
one method for uh fixed delay, one
method for jitterness and they have
their logic how to compute the delay
next delay.
So that is first thing. So we have to
have one interval function method where
we write our delay logic.
Generally this would be we have to
implement it only in case we have to
write for custom logic. But in case if
you are using already present one then
we just need to call that which method
internally.
Then second is retry config like here we
set the configurations like uh attempt
attempt number equals to four. Then wait
time something something. So all the
configuration generally we will put it
here. And then is retry object. From
this config a retry object is created
which will be used to do the retry.
we so if you see that we don't have to
do anything we just do this AOP writes
the code what I am saying is what AOP
how AOP might be doing this or computing
this code so now this is the part so
first it is getting retry config dot
custom
it is setting the configuration let's
say max attemp was four that's what we
have defined here right in the
configuration
max attempt 3 4
like these are the configuration I mean
right so you can say max attemp four
interval function which interval
function you have to call so let's say I
am using fixed interval okay so it will
call this method interval function dot
off so I have defined delay is 2 seconds
so this method takes
interval function dot of
2 seconds it is in millisecond generally
it takes Okay. Then on what all
exceptions you have to retry on what all
exceptions you have to retry you can add
it here also.
Okay.
And uh finally you do build. So you got
the retry config and from that retry
config retry do. You can create an
object of the retry. Just give whatever
the name you wanted to give your retry
and this config. So it will create an
object from this config retry config.
Okay. So first thing is the interval
function method which has to be invoked.
So how AOP knows that which one by
default is
in the configuration by default is fixed
interval and we haven't tell anything
explicitly that we want that. So by
default it take fixed interval one
configuration we have already provided
what is the max time and what is the
wait time. Okay and even the retry what
on on what on exceptions you want to
retry
right that also we can define in the
config.
So this is how internally it might be
doing it.
So let's see exponential back off. So
all same only configuration changes. See
this code we don't have to write this
will return by AOP. So this is just for
understanding purpose what AOP might be
doing it inside. So this retry thing
nothing changed. So we still on whatever
method you have to do a retry please
double check on that you have to write
this annotation. The only thing change
is that our
configuration. So here if you see for
exponential backoff these are the
configuration we have to give. So see if
you go into the back of Java class this
is the formula they have written the
same thing what we have written right
initial weight time into whatever the
factor 2 3 raised to power number of
failed retry attempt. So this is the
formula they have written in their back
of Java class also. This is a framework
class you can check it.
So maximum attempt is four original plus
three retry.
Okay. Wait duration is first second. So
weight duration this is the initial
weight time. So 1 second is my initial
weight time.
Enable exponential backoff true because
this is not the default uh strategy for
retry. Right? So that's why I'm
explicitly saying hey enable the
exponential backoff. True.
What is the factor you want to use?
Exponential back off multiplier is two.
I want 2 raised to power. If you make it
three it would be like 3 to power. Okay.
So this is this factor part.
So this is your formula going to be so
first retry after let's say original
happen at 0 second. The first retry will
happen at initial is 1 second. So let's
say 1,000 millisecond into what is the
factor we told 2 raised to power number
of failed retry at time currently is
zero. So after first second the first
retry will happen second will happen and
after 2 second third will happen at 4
second like this.
So actually we are going with zero in
the formula they have just says that
iteration minus one. So retry iteration
generally. So currently it is the first
retry. So that's why it started with
zero. No retry has failed failure till
now. The same thing different way to
understand like how you can remember it.
So let's analyze the output here. If you
see that what is the maximum attempt we
have told four means one original and
three retry.
So if you see that original call happen
at 212240
then it does the first retry at 212241
second delay.
After that it do a second retry at 43
2cond delay. Then the third retry 47 4
secondond delay and since all the ret
attempts finished four attemp finish our
fallback method executed.
Okay. So this is how exponential backup
works and if you see the AOP generated
code you actually you can't see if you
just try to analyze it again the three
part first is interval function we have
to tell so internally since we have make
this true
enable exponential backup. Now AOP might
be adding this method of interval
function exponential
not random there is another method. So
this is we are not using jitter one
right. So this would be like off
exponential back off. There is one more
flavor of exponential random back off
which is for the third jitterness one.
Okay. But but I think you got it like
based on the what we tell in the
configuration explicitly
that method would be invoked. So this is
the place where the actual delay logic
is computed. Then retry config
where we have like what is the maximum
attempt what is the retry on the
exception you have to do retry
and from this config you have to create
create and retry object
this is again just for our understanding
you can't debug that code it it is
generated by AOP dynamically at runtime
similarly for exponential backoff plus
jitter No change you have to use the
same annotation add the rate retry no
difference in that only difference in
the configuration and you know that
everything journals is exactly same as
exponential backoff but only thing is
enable randomized weight that's all
some random thing has been added we just
have to enable that hey use random so
now here it will use this random back
off method for computation
Okay,
then we have custom retry. Now this is
interesting part. Now we have to retry,
right? So first thing first, we can't
use at the rate retry annotation now
because when we use at the rate retry
what generally happen is our AOP depends
upon configuration to construct the to
create a retry object. But now since
there is no configuration
right we can't use this annotation that
will not work. So one thing is we have
to manually create a retry object. Now
our understanding of that will come into
this picture. So here what I am doing
now. So here if you see that
in the add the rate configuration I have
written a method custom retry. I am
creating a bean. I'm creating an object
of retry.
So this is we know that AOP might be
doing it and the same thing I am doing
the first thing is interval function. So
we have to provide a function method
which
where the delay computation would be
calculated. So here is Fibonacci
interval. So here earlier I what I did
is like I have like I want to run it
like one one then two then three then
five like this. So first retry happen at
one. Another retry happen at one. Uh the
third retry happen after 2 seconds. U
then three. Then like this in Fibonacci
way the delay increases. But for
simplification purpose you can have all
this logic here. This is just for demo
purpose that
different logic you can build. But here
I am just for simplification purpose.
I'm just returning what is the delay
time it return.
Right? For each
run, for each retry, we have to compute
the delay time. Right? What is the next
delay time? What is the next delay time?
So, this method returns the duration
like
wait for this much sec milliseconds.
Wait for this much duration. Okay. So
let's say that Fibonacci interval you
have the logic all here and it return
milliseconds later. Let's say it return
this one
2 millisecond it has to wait. Okay. So
this generally method do the computation
again and return what time
retry what has to let's say if it is
third retry. If it is third retry, so
retry one, retry two, retry three, then
it will return 2 seconds, 2,000
millisecond.
Got it? So we have to write this method
now. And this is what first thing I have
done.
So attempt
for each attempt. So let's say if you
are four attempt for each attempt it
compute the duration delay time.
The second thing is same retry config
max attempt you have to now tell it here
there is no configuration
application.properties you have to tell
it here retry exception what what all
exception you have to do retry you you
don't have to define it
application.properties properties you
have to define it here dot build your
config object is created and from that
you create a retry object so now we have
created the retry object now we have to
use it how to use it now now in the
order service on this product API
we can't uh do annotation right at the
rate retry we can't do that so we have
to do this way and that's what
internally AOP might be doing that also.
So first it has created a retry object
like this what we have done and then it
would have in the similar way it might
have done the same way. So
it autowired the custom retry object the
retry object which we have created the
bean which we have created. So here
dependency injection will happen.
Then it has execute supplier. Okay. So
we are wrapping what we are doing is we
are wrapping an object. So this is I
want to retry this is my retriable
code. I am wrapping it inside this retry
dot
retry. I'm wrapping wrapping it up
within this retry
because annotation will not work. I have
to do it manually. So this is my piece
of code which I want to do retry in case
of failure.
Now I have to manually wrap it inside
the custom retry dot execute supplier.
Okay. Now let's say that you have you
have invoked it. There is a failure. So
it will automatically retry it. Okay.
Because it is inside the retry object,
right? For each retry we have done
attempt, right? For each retry it find
out the delay it has to wait based on
the logic you have written. It will find
out what is the delay time it has to
wait and after waiting for that much
time
right it will execute again based on
this configuration if that exception is
retrivable and if attempt is still left
if all the attempt is finished then
ultimately this catch block will get
invoked all retries failed this is the
fallback. So by writing this custom
retry by ourself we get to know that
what AOP might be doing inside. So you
can say that this is the exact AOP code
which might they have done during
runtime. First they have created a retry
object and then for that retry object
they have wrapped it the method which we
have written right at the rate retry
before they wrap those method
inside this custom retry dot execute
supplier.
Okay. And after all retry finish
in the catch part it might have run our
fallback method
and we can check our output also. So we
have done
six attempts right
one original five retry. So we can say
so what is our uh code which have to be
retried one is system.out.print
calling product service and the time and
then actually it's called it. So these
two things will get think. So original
happen at this calling product service
and then it will try to call it. So it
happened at 22 35 45. Then here if you
see 47 49 51 22 second delay. Why 22cond
delay? Because currently I have
hardcoded it to 2,00 millisecond. Here
if you can see I have hardcoded it to
2,000 millisecond. That's why. But if
you have returned your own interval that
if it is a retry one one retry two again
one if it is a retry three 2 seconds if
it is a retry fourth three retry fifth
like this then eight like this it it
should go then 13
so then it will change it but for now
since I have hardcoded it so for each
retry attempt when it tried to compute
what is the duration I have to wait it
will always return two 2 seconds itself.
So that's why it is waited 2 seconds. So
1 2 3 4 5 6 attempt finished. Then it
reached to the else part. Fall back
here. All retries failed. This is fall
back. All retries failed. This is fall
back.
I hope got it right because to be honest
at least in this 10 years I haven't
written custom retry
generally exponential backup with jitter
is sufficient right with little work on
this values but if you have to write it
this way you can write it or if you have
to understand like how this
with just putting annot annotation
with just putting this annotation this
one.
How internally everything work by AOP
then it is exactly same as what custom
we have written. Create an object of
retry
define what is the method you have to
use interval function for computation
and then ultimately wrap your method
inside this retry object.
Okay. So let me know if there is any
doubt we can discuss further into the
comment section. But till then bye.